When you used the rubber band with dogs eat bones, and when you built your own
sentence, you saw that intonation reduces the unstressed words. Intonation is the
peak, and reduced sounds are the valleys. In the beginning, you should make extra
high peaks in long, deep valleys. When you're not sure, reduce. In the following
exercise, work with this idea. Small words such as articles, prepositions, pronouns,
conjunctions, relative pronouns, and auxiliary verbs are lightly skimmed over
and almost not pronounced. You've seen how intonation changes the meaning in words
and sentences. Inside a one-syllable word, it distinguishes between a final-voiced or
unvoiced consonant, bad and bet. Inside a longer word, unique versus unique, the
pronunciation and meaning change in terms of vocabulary. In a sentence, he seems
nice, he seems nice, the meaning changes in terms of intent. In a sentence,
intonation can also make a clear vowel sound disappear. When a vowel is stressed,
it has a certain sound. When it's not stressed, it usually sounds like UH,
pronounced uh. Small words like to, at, or as are not usually stressed, so the vowel
disappears.